Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbooks Collection UA118
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbooks Collection
1858 -- 1905
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts College
UA118
19.35 Linear Feet 17 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Custodial History
These albums were discovered by chance in the stacks. Some were owned by Tufts and others donated by students or their families. Albums with "Library" embedded in the cover are assumed to have been the library's copy, and albums with a personal name are assumed to have been a student's personal copy. Some albums have an inscription in the front cover designating ownership and year donated to Tufts.
Scope and Contents
These 45 photograph albums contain images of Tufts University faculty and graduating classes from 1858-1898. Graduating students could order which images they wanted to have included and thus volumes from the same year might contain different photographs. Other images may include group photos, campus and Medford-area landscapes and buildings, non-faculty staff, and family members. There are gaps in years throughout the collection. One album does not have a date. The condition of the albums has deteriorated and they should be handled with extreme care. Most of the photographs are identified and some have personal signatures or salutations written on or around the photograph. Also, the backs of photographs may have notes or names but only if conditions allow should they be examined.
Biographical / Historical
Tufts College was founded in 1852 by a group of Universalists who had for years worked to open a non-sectarian institution of higher learning.
By 1830, Universalist efforts to build an institution of higher learning were increasing in both frequency and strength. Many Universalist ministers and laymen alike felt that their community needed a school that intertwined theological and liberal arts courses. Their opponents, however, feared the creation of a theological institution, as they felt it would create clerical domination, and prevent uneducated but devoted Universalists from becoming clergymen.
In 1835, at the annual General Convention, Thomas Jefferson Sawyer, a prominent Universalist, put forth a recommendation calling for the question of establishing a Theological Seminary to be put to the denomination at large. The resolution was adopted, and for the next four years, Sawyer's colleague, Reverend Thomas Whittemore, worked tirelessly to drum up support, both through columns in the Universalist paper, "The Trumpet," and through speeches.
By this time it had become clear that a Universalist theological college was a necessary step for the advancement of the religion. Hosea Ballou 2nd, a prolific writer and well-known minister, served as a teacher for many young Universalists interested in joining the clergy. The demand for his teaching had become so great that he had begun to teach classes instead of individual students. This high demand illustrated the need for an official school, planned for either upstate New York or the Boston, Massachusetts, area.
At the Massachusetts State Convention in 1840, attendees authorized the creation of a board of trustees to raise funds, find a site, and erect the buildings for a Universalist college. The committee included both Hosea Ballou and his son, Hosea Ballou 2nd. After the creation of the board, serious fundraising began, with a goal of $50,000 set for the campaign. Due to a lack of popular support and internal tension on the board, the first effort eventually failed.
In 1847, another fundraising drive began, this time with a goal of $100,000. Otis Skinner, another prominent Universalist, was selected to head the fundraising team. By 1851, Skinner and his team had reached the goal. By this time, the trustees had also selected the site of the future college. Earlier in the decade, Charles Tufts had donated $20,000 worth of Medford land to the trustees with the stipulation that the college be built on the site. This caused a rift among the trustees. Some felt that the college belonged in New York, others voted for Springfield, and even Hosea Ballou 2nd felt that the Tufts location was too close to Harvard and Boston. The question was put to a vote, and eventually the Medford site prevailed.
On April 22, 1852, Massachusetts granted a charter to the Trustees of Tufts College for the establishment of an institution of higher learning. The now official Trustees attempted to elect Thomas Jefferson Sawyer as the first president of Tufts, but his salary demands were too high. By 1853, Hosea Ballou 2nd had been selected as the institution's first president. By the fall of 1854, Tufts College, though not yet formally opened, had begun operation. On August 22, 1855, the college held a formal opening, and the first formal term saw over thirty students enrolled.
Tufts College continued as a liberal arts institution until the fall of 1869, when the Divinity School officially opened. In his will, benefactor Sylvanius Packard had earmarked $300,000 for Tufts, but stipulated that part of the trust must go to the establishment of a Professorship of Christian Theology. Hoping to remain a non-sectarian school, Tufts instead opted to found a separate and quasi-independent Divinity School. In 1906, the Divinity School was renamed the Crane Theological School, and continued operation until 1968.
The next major event in early Tufts history was the decision to become a co-educational institution. After ten years of debate, the Trustees finally decided to bring women to Tufts College in 1892. Although men and women originally took classes together, Tufts provided separate housing and dining facilities. By the first decade of the twentieth century, however, many administrators were becoming more and more opposed to co-education. Tufts had seen a drop in male enrollment, and many worried that it was because of the presence of women in classes. Women had also begun to dominate academically. In 1906, for example, all five seniors elected to Phi Beta Kappa were female. The co-education question was solved in 1910 using funds from an 1895 grant. Cornelia Marie Jackson had left half of her estate to Tufts to improve facilities for women, including a stipulation that a building be constructed and named The Cornelia M. Jackson College for Women. In 1910, the Trustees decided to use Jackson's funds to create a coordinate college. Jackson was to be separate from Tufts, with female only classes, dormitories, and dining halls. The Trustees felt it was the best way to improve male enrollment without alienating women. Male and female students remained segregated until 1913, when classes were again made co-educational.
Soon after Tufts became co-educational, an opportunity for a new branch of the college appeared in Boston. In 1893, seven faculty members from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, dissatisfied with their employer, left the school and with the backing of Tufts College formed the Tufts School of Medicine. The downtown Boston school soon spawned another branch. In 1899, Tufts acquired the Boston Dental College, and the renamed Tufts School of Dental Medicine began operation in close coordination with the Tufts School of Medicine.
Tufts continued its expansion into the twentieth century. In 1933, with a bequest from trustee Austin B. Fletcher, Tufts opened the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. The school, opened with the collaboration of Harvard University, became the first graduate school of international affairs in the United States. It also brought tremendous prestige to Tufts, which was quickly gaining a reputation as an excellent school.
Expansion continued into the 1940's, when Tufts allied with the Bouve-Boston School of Physical Therapy and Physical Education in 1942. In 1945, Tufts formed alliances with both the School of the Museum of Fine Arts and the Boston School of Occupational Therapy. In 1951, Tufts began operating the Boston Nursery Training School as a separate entity under the College of Special Studies. In 1955, the school was renamed the Eliot Pearson Children's School.
1955 brought another important change for Tufts. A petition from the Trustees dated January 20, 1955, and approved on January 28, officially changed the name of the school to Tufts University. The name change, one of President Nils Y. Wessell's original goals, was cited as both an official recognition of an already established event, and also as a recognition of a desirable direction for Tufts to move in.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Student life; Curriculum and Instruction -- Faculty
- Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbooks, 1858 -- 1905; 1858 -- 1898; UA118.001; 17.3 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 45 photograph albums with images of Tufts University faculty and graduating classes from 1858-1898. Other images may include group photos, campus and Medford-area landscapes and buildings, non-faculty staff, and family members. There are gaps in years throughout the collection. One album does not have a date. The condition of the albums has deteriorated and they should be handled with extreme care. Most of the photographs are identified and some have personal signatures or salutations written on or around the photograph. Also, the backs of photographs may have notes or names but only if conditions allow should they be examined.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged loosely chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Tufts First Regular Class, 1858 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students, campus, buildings. Portraits identified and signed. Front inside cover reads, "From the estate of A.E. Scott, 1858, April 1945." Letter dated 1868 inserted in binding.
  - JJ Lewis [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1863; UA118.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students. Portraits identified. Photos include year of photo and where it was taken. Front cover reads, "From the library of Professor J.R. Lewis, 1887."
  - Fred C. Nash [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1863; UA118.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students. Piece of blue cloth between pages.
  - Thompson [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1863; UA118.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students. Portraits identified and signed. Photos include year of photo and where it was taken.
  - Class of '67 Tufts College [Faculty and Senior Class Yearbook], 1867; UA118.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students, buildings. Portraits identified.
  - The Faculty and Class of 1867, Tufts College [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    Faculty, students. Portraits identified and signed.
  - The Faculty and Class of 1868, Tufts College [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Charles E. Fay [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1868; UA118.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Tufts College [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1869; UA118.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    Faculty, students, group shots, buildings. Portraits identified.
  - D. Merle Teele [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1870; UA118.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Tufts College Class of 1870 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Tufts College [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1871; UA118.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - FM Hawes [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1872; UA118.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
    Faculty, students, campus, buildings. Portraits identified.
  - FW Knowlton/ Tufts College Class of '72 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1872; UA118.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
    Faculty, students, campus, buildings.
  - '73 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1873; UA118.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - '74 Henry Priest [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1874; UA118.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
    Faculty, students, Medford area, campus, buildings. Some portraits identified. Donated to Tufts in 1945 by Mrs. Ward C. Priest. Grade report between pages.
  - Norman P. Wood '74 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1874; UA118.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
    Faculty, students, campus, and buildings.
  - Tufts College Class of 1875 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    Faculty, students, buildings, campus. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts College Class of 1875 [Faculty and Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
    Faculty, students, campus and area landscapes, buildings. Inscription on inside front cover reads, "Donated to United Methodist Church in 1959." Possibly belonged to John T. Baber Sr.
  - Tufts College Divinity School, Class of 1875 [Faculty and Class Photograph Yearbook], UA118.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
    Faculty and students. Portraits identified. Photos include a date.
  - [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook, circa 1875-1905], UA118.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
    Faculty and students. Portraits identified. Years unknown but estimated from picture of President Elmer Hewitt Capen (1875-1905). If the women in the album are students then this album could not have been created before 1893.
  - '76 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1876; UA118.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
    Faculty, students, buildings, and campus. Portraits identified and some signed.
  - Tufts '77 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1877; UA118.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
    Faculty, students, buildings, and campus. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts '78 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1878; UA118.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
    Faculty, students. Portraits identified. Index of names on front cover.
  - '79 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1879; UA118.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
    Faculty, seniors, buildings, and campus. Portraits identified.
  - George A. Gardner [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1880; UA118.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
    Faculty, students, buildings, group shot. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts College '81 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1881; UA118.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
    Faculty, students, group shot. Portraits identified. Some contain year deceased and professor's subject area.
  - Library [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1881; UA118.001.007.00002 (Box 7)
    Faculty, students, group shots.
  - Tufts College Class of '82 Library [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbooks], 1882; UA118.001.007.00003 (Box 7)
    Students. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts College '83 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1883; UA118.001.008.00001 (Box 8)
  - Tufts College Class of '84, Charles P. Stevens [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook, 1884, complete], UA118.001.008.00002 (Box 8)
    Gift by Laurie Le Page in June, 2009. Faculty, students, campus, buildings. Additional copy can be found at 39090015513159, this version does not have all campus buildings but does have some identified students.
  - Library Class of '85 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1885; UA118.001.009.00001 (Box 9)
    Students. Portraits identified and signed. Images also note where the person is from.
  - Tufts College Class of '86, Harry L. Canfield [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1886; UA118.001.009.00002 (Box 9)
    Faculty, students, group photos, campus and Medford-area landscapes and buildings. Some portraits identified. Some contain graduation year and professor's subject area.
  - Leo R. Lewis [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1887; UA118.001.009.00003 (Box 9)
    Faculty, students, group photos. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts College '88, Thomas O. Marvin [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1888; UA118.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
    Faculty, students, buildings, group shots. Portraits identified. May be signed on back.
  - Tufts Class of '89 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1889; UA118.001.010.00002 (Box 10)
    Students. Portraits identified and signed.
  - JB Pattee, Tufts '90 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1890; UA118.001.010.00003 (Box 10)
    Faculty and students. Portraits identified and signed.
  - Library Class of '91 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1891; UA118.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
  - Tufts College '92, Maro Spaulding Brooks [Faculty and Senior Class Photographic Yearbook], 1892; UA118.001.012.00001 (Box 12)
    Faculty, students, unidentified women. Portraits identified and signed.
  - Tufts College '92, Joseph F. Cobb [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1892; UA118.001.012.00002 (Box 12)
    Faculty, students, building interiors, buildings, Cora Cobb. Portraits identified. Commencement program on inside front cover.
  - Tufts College '93 Library [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1893; UA118.001.013.00001 (Box 13)
    Students, one woman. Portraits identified.
  - Tufts College Class of '94 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1894; UA118.001.013.00002 (Box 13)
    Students. Portraits identified and signed on backs.
  - Tufts College Class of '95 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1895; UA118.001.013.00003 (Box 13)
  - Tufts College '96 Class Album [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1896; UA118.001.014.00001 (Box 14)
    Students and first women graduates. Portraits identified and signed.
  - Tufts College Class of '98 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1898; UA118.001.014.00002 (Box 14)
    Students. Portraits identified and some signed. Class Day pamphlet inside front cover.
  - Tufts College Class of '84 Chase F. Spear [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph yearbook], 1884; UA118.001.015.00001 (Box 15)
    Incomplete yearbook. Please see complete version at 390900114011486. Faculty, students, campus, buildings, and some identified students.
  - Tufts College '88, Lewis D. Coburn [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1888; UA118.001.016.00001 (Box 16)
    Faculty, students, buildings, group shots. Some portraits identified. May be signed on back. Donated by Coburn's granddaughter, Carolyn Coburn Sieven, August 2010. Stored in unbuffered paper.
  - Tufts College Class of '94 [Faculty and Senior Class Photograph Yearbook], 1894; UA118.001.017.00001 (Box 17)